<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doctrine of the Lords supper By way of question and answer, gathered out of 1. Corint. chap. 11. ver. 23. to 33. By Charles Richardson, preacher at S. Katharins neare the Tower of London.</title>
            <author>Richardson, Charles, fl. 1612-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119813</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855019</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855019</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20489</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20489)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1556:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doctrine of the Lords supper By way of question and answer, gathered out of 1. Corint. chap. 11. ver. 23. to 33. By Charles Richardson, preacher at S. Katharins neare the Tower of London.</title>
                  <author>Richardson, Charles, fl. 1612-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Lionell Snowdon, for W. Butlar, and are to be sold at his shop in the Bulwarke, neare the Tower of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20489:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20489:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DOCTRINE OF THE LORDS SVPPER.</p>
            <p>By way of Queſtion and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Gathered out of 1. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. chap.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 23. to 33.</p>
            <p>By CHARLES RICHARDSON, Preacher at S. Katharins <hi>neare the Tower of</hi> London.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Lionell Snowdon,</hi> for <hi>W. But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in the Bulwarke, neare the Tower of London. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20489:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20489:2"/>
            <head>¶ To my Chriſtian <hi>Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours at</hi> S. Katharines <hi>neare the</hi> Tower, increaſe of all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing graces.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Auditours, though among all the parts of Gods ſeruice, which wee are bound to performe, there are none more excellent, nor more honourable, then the worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of his holy &amp; bleſſed Supper: yet it is fearefull and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſee, how much it is generally abuſed and profaned in the world. Some are ignorant, and vnderſtand nothing at all of the true vſe of the Sacrament. As our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> ſaid to the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 4.22</note> 
               <hi>Yee worſhip that which ye know not:</hi> ſo it may be truely ſaid to many at this day, <hi>They receiue that which they know not.</hi> They haue no iudgement to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Lords body,</hi> and therefore they ruſh vpon theſe holy <hi>Myſteries</hi> without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence.
<pb facs="tcp:20489:3"/>
Others are notoriouſly wicked, holding their ſins in their right hand.<note place="margin">Ierem. 7.9, 10</note> They will <hi>ſteale, murther, and commit adultery, and ſweare falſly &amp;c.</hi> As the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith, &amp; yet thinke they may <hi>come and ſtand before God in his houſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 7.6</note> and though in the ſight of God, they be no better then filthy <hi>dogges and ſwine:</hi> yet they will preſume to ſit as gueſts at his Table. Others againe there are, that haue both know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and grace in ſome meaſure, and yet for want of due preparation, come many times to the Lords Supper, without that reuerence that is required.</p>
            <p>For the reforming of all theſe abuſes, I haue in your hearing handled in many Sermons, the Doctrine of this Sacrament, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath ſet it downe. And for the helpe of thoſe that are ignorant, I haue drawne the ſumme of all that was publikely taught, into ſhort Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and Anſwers, which here I commend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, as an vnfained teſtimony of my loue. I confeſſe I owe much vnto you, for the great kindeneſſe which I daily receiue at your hands. For as you entertained me at my firſt comming with a generall conſent:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.3</note> ſo I <hi>beare you record, that to your power,</hi> yea and many of you, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond your power,</hi> are willing to giue me bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter maintenance (conſidering the pouerty of the
<pb facs="tcp:20489:3"/>
place) then many richer Pariſhes about the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie doe affoord. All that I can doe, is to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue my paines among you, as I haue begunne ſo long as it ſhall pleaſe God. And I deſire you all to labour together in prayer for me, that I may with all faithfulneſſe <hi>fulfill the Miniſterie that I haue receiued of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 4.17.</note> Thus hoping you will accept this ſmall gift of mine, with the ſame affection that I offer it, I commend you all to the grace of God, beſeeching him, to <hi>make your hearts ſtable and vnblameable in holineſſe before God, euen our Father, at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt with all his Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, CHARLES RICHARDSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="doctrine">
            <pb facs="tcp:20489:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20489:4"/>
            <head>THE DOCTRINE OF THE LORDS SVPPER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat doeth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſet downe in this portion of Scripture?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Which are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> The true inſtitution of the Lords Supper, to the <hi>27.</hi> verſe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2,</hi> The right vſe thereof in the reſt of the verſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is to be obſerued in the firſt part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> A Preface. <hi>2.</hi> The Inſtitution it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. What are the words of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:5"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> I haue receiued of the Lord, that which I alſo haue deliuered vnto you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doe you learne from hence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> It teacheth Miniſters, that they muſt deliuer nothing to the people concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Doctrine of faith and manners, but what they haue receiued and learned of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s 17.11 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn 4.1</note>
               <hi>2.</hi> It teacheth the people to receiue no doctrine, but that which is agréeable to the Word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q How many things are to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the Inſtitution of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Foure things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> The Author of it: <hi>2.</hi> the time when it was ordayned: <hi>3.</hi> the patres: <hi>4</hi> the end of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Who was the Author of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth that teach vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> That none hath power to make Sacraments, but Chriſt onely.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 5.7 and 26.6 Exodus 20.7</note>
               <hi>2.</hi> That wee muſt bring reuerence with vs when we come to receiue becauſe it is not the ordinance of man, but of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:5"/>
               <hi>Q. At what time did Chriſt ordaine it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the ſame night that he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth that teach vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To make great account of the Lords Supper, as being the laſt gift that Chriſt left to his Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How many parts are there of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſignes, and the actions to be performed about the ſignes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What be the ſignes in the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Bread and Wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth the Bread ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The body of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. What reſemblance is there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Bread &amp; the Body of Chriſt?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5.8, 9</note> As bread is baked in the Ouen by the heate of the fire: ſo the body of Chriſt, being as it were baked in the fire of the Croſſe, is made the bread of life.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 11.28 Ieremy 29.13</note> As bread is moſt eaſily gotten of all food: ſo Chriſt is eaſily found of all that truely and ſeaſonably ſake him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:6"/>
               <hi>Q. Why did our Sauiour Chriſt make choice of bread, rather then of fleſh to ſignifie his body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 104 15</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he did not ſo much reſpect the colour and outward forme, as the ſtrength of nouriſhing, which is greater in bread then in fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth the Wine ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> The bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. What reſemblance is there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the wine and the bloud of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> As wine flowing from the grape, is the ſwéeteſt of all licours: ſo the bloud of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iohn 6.55</note> who is the true Vine, flowing from his ſide, is the ſweeteſt drinke of the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> As wine doth cleare and refreſh the heart of man:<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.55</note> ſo the bloud of Chriſt ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled vpon the heart, doth comfort the ſoule of euery beléeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why hath our Sauiour ordained both bread and wine to be ſignes in this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To teach vs, that in him there is full and perfect nouriſhment and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for vs.<note place="margin">Pſal 130 7 Acts. 4.12</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth this admoniſh vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5.6</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> That wee muſt bring to the Lords
<pb facs="tcp:20489:6"/>
Table an earneſt deſire of Chriſt and his grace: we muſt both hunger and thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q Is it not lawfull to adminiſter the Lords Supper vnder one ſigne, as the Papiſts doe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, not without great iniury to Chriſt and his Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. What iniury is done to Chriſt thereby?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is a mangling of his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,<note place="margin">Apoc. 22.18, 19 Galat. 3.15</note> and a detracting from his laſt will and Teſtament: both which are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. What iniury is done to the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The conſcience of the godly are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of that moſt ſwéete promiſe which Chriſt hath annexed to the Cup.<note place="margin">Matth. 26.28</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are the actions to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the adminiſtration of theſe ſigns?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Some of them were performed by Chriſt, and are now to be performed by the Miniſter: and ſome by the Diſciples to be done by the receiuers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are the actions to be done by the Miniſter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are thrée.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:7"/>
               <hi>Q. What is the firſt of them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To take the bread and wine, and to bleſſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What meane you by that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.5 1 Sam. 9.13</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> By prayer to ſeparate them, that they may be ſacramentall bread and wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth this action ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 10.36 and 6.27</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> That Chriſt Ieſus was ſet apart, by the Father, to be the Redeemer of the Elect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How was Chriſt ſet apart to this worke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thrée wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.20 Galat. 4.4 Matt. 3.16, 17</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> In Gods eternall decree.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> In his incarnation.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> In his baptiſme.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth this action admoniſh vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.1 Pro. 23.26</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That wee muſt likewiſe ſet our ſelues apart to his ſeruice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſecond action to bee done by the Miniſter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To breake the bread, and to powre out the Wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth this action ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 53.4, 5 1 Pet. 2.24 Matt. 20.28</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> That Chriſt his body was broken with ſorrow, and his bloud ſhed vpon the
<pb facs="tcp:20489:7"/>
Croſſe for our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth it admoniſh vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zech. 12.10 2 Sam. 24.17</note> That our ſoules ſhould bléede with remorce and ſorrow for ſinne.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 2.20</note> That we muſt for euer loathe and deteſt our ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.24 1 Theſſ. 1.6 Matth. 20.22</note> That wee muſt be content to ſuffer any thing for Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Mat. 10.38.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. What is the third action to bee done by the Miniſter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To giue the bread and wine to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery particular receiuer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat doth this action ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That God doth likewiſe giue Chriſt Ieſus with all his merits to euerie true beleeuer.<note place="margin">Iohn 3.16</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat doth it admoniſh vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.20 1 Pet. 1 17, 18, 19</note> That we muſt wholly giue our ſelues backe againe to Chriſt</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That we muſt be willing for Chriſt his ſake to giue ſomewhat to the reliefe of our poore brethren.<note place="margin">1 Iohn 3.17 and 4 11</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What words did our Sauior Chriſt vſe in adminiſtring theſe ſignes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Words of promiſe concerning the Bread and the Cup.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat are he words concerning the Bread?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:8"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> This is my body which is broken for you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. What is the meaning of theſe words?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Geneſis 17, 10, 11 and 41.26, 27 Exudus 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.13 1 Cor. 10.4</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> This bread is a ſigne to repreſent, and a ſeale to ſeale vnto you my body, with the benefites of my paſſion ſuffered in the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What may we learne from thence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The great goodneſſe of God to his Church, that hath not only giuen vs his word and promiſes: but for the better ſtrengthning of our faith, hath alſo giuen vs his Sacraments, to ſeale the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is not the bread really turned into the body of Chriſt, after theſe words be pronounced by the Prieſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, by no meanes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhy ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> Becauſe it ouerthroweth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How prooue you that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe in euery Sacrament there muſt be theſe two things: the ſigne, and the thing ſignified. But if the bread ceaſe to be bread, and be turned into the body of Chriſt, then the Sacrament hath loſt his
<pb facs="tcp:20489:8"/>
outward Signe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhy elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is plaine in the text, that our Sauiour Chriſt tooke the bread and wine into his hand: he brake the one, and powred out the other, and did himſelfe eat and drinke the ſame. Now none of all theſe can bee true of the reall body and bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhy elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Becauſe the Bread is called the Communion of the body of Chriſt:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not his body it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhy elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the Apoſtle calleth it bread ſtill after the conſecration, to teach vs,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.26, 27, 28</note> that the ſubſtance of bread remaineth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhy elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe diuerſe abſurdities would otherwiſe follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 28.6 Acts 1.9, 11 and 3.21</note> That Chriſts body ſhould be in many places at once, which is contrary to the nature of a true body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That Chriſt ſhould haue two bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: one borne of the Virgine <hi>Mary,</hi> and another made of the bread.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:9"/>
               <hi>Q. VVhat elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That we ſhould not in the Lords Supper receiue the body of Chriſt, that was crucified for vs, but an other body made by the Prieſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. But may not this be done by a miracle?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhy ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An. 1.</hi> Becauſe Miracles are ceaſed: neyther haue the Prieſts now anie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Exodus 4.3, 4 Iohn 2.7, 8, 9</note>2 Becauſe in euery Miracle there is a viſible and ſenſible change. But heere is no ſuch thing we ſee, and feele, and taſte bread ſtill, as we did before.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Becauſe Miracles, though they be beyond and aboue nature, yet they are not againſt nature to ouerthrow it as this doth, in making the finite body of Chriſt to be in many places at once.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Becauſe a Miracle is an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie worke of God, belonging to certaine times and perſons. But the Sacraments are for all times, and for the whole church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. But can not God by his omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie doe this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Wee are not in this caſe to reſpect
<pb facs="tcp:20489:9"/>
what God can doe, but what hee will doe: now he hath not any where reuealed that he will doe this, and therefore we are not to beléeue it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are the words concerning the Cuppe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This Cup is the new Teſtament in my bloud, which is ſhed for you,<note place="margin">Matt. 26.28 Luke 22.20</note> and for many for the remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. VVhat is the meaning of theſe words?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Cup, that is, the wine in the Cup which I offer vnto you, is a pledge and ſeale of my Teſtament, to eſtabliſh and confirme the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is meant by the word Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Eyther a Couenant or a laſt Will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How many kinds of Couenants is there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Two: the couenant of Workes, and the couenant of Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is the couenant of Works?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a compact of perfect obedience to the will of God,<note place="margin">Leuit. 18.5</note> vpon condition of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life if it be obeyed, and of eternall death if it be not obeyed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:10"/>
               <hi>Q. Is any man able to keepe this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.23</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, for all haue ſinned, and are are depriued of the glory of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is the couenant of grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 31.31, 32, 33</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a compact of mutu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation betwéene God and man, in and through Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVherein conſiſteth that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ieremy 31.34</note>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> In a gracious promiſe of remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins, and euerlaſting life on Gods part.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Marke 1.15</note>
               <hi>2.</hi> In faith in Gods promiſes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance on mans part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. VVhat reſemblance is betweene this Couenant, and a laſt will or Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> As he that maketh the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hath no benefite by it himſelfe: ſo Chriſt no benefite by this Couenant, but all redoundeth to the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9.16, 17.</note>
               <hi>Anſ. 2.</hi> As a Teſtament is neuer of force till the Teſtator be dead: ſo this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant was made effectuall by the death of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why is it called a new Teſtament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To diſtinguiſh it from the old Te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtament,
<pb facs="tcp:20489:10"/>
that was made with the Fathers before Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Was not the couenant of Grace in the Lawe, the ſame that is in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes: For ſubſtance, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of all the cauſes it was one and the ſame.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 9.5 2 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.9</note> The efficient cauſe of both is the méere mercy of God, without any reſpect of workes.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> The matter of both is Chriſt,<note place="margin">Geneſis 3.15 and 12.3 2 Cor. 5.19 Heb. 13.8 Apoc. 13, 8 Heb. 11. tot Rom 4.23, 24 Heb. 11.9, 10, 13 Gen. 47.9 Num 23 to Pſal. 116.15.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom no man is receiued into Gods fauour.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> The formall cauſe of them both is faith.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> The end whereunto they bother cited men, is eternall life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. How then doe they differ one from another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1</hi> The promiſes in the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were for the moſt part of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bleſſings, but the promiſes in the new Teſtament, are of ſpirituall.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> In the olde Teſtament there were many ceremonies and ſacrifices, burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and coſtly: in the new Teſtament there are but a few, &amp; they light and eaſie.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:11"/>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 11.13 Heb. 11.13 Iohn 1.29 Galat. 3.1</note>
               <hi>3.</hi> In the olde Teſtament, all things were deliuered obſcurely, in Types and Figures: but in the new Teſtament, the myſterie of our ſaluation is plainely and openly reuealed.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">Iohn 7.38, 39 Acts 2.17 Ierem. 31.14</note>
               <hi>4.</hi> There is ordinarily a greater mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the graces of Gods Spirite in the New Teſtament, then there was in the Olde.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.8, 9 Matth. 10.5, 6 Marke 16.15 Acts 10.15, 34 Rom. 3.29 Epheſ. 2.14, 15</note>
               <hi>5.</hi> The New Teſtament is made knowne to more people then the old was. For that was only knowne to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> but this is publiſhed to all nations.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> In the old Teſtament Chriſt was onely promiſed,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.20 2 Tim. 1.9, 10</note> but in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he is exhibited.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. Why was it neceſſary that the bloud of our Sauiour Chriſt ſhould bee ſhed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. 1.</hi> Becauſe it was figured in the olde Teſtament, in the Paſchall Lambe, and in the Sacrifices.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 17.11. Heb. 9.22.</note>
               <hi>2.</hi> That hee might make his ſacrifice perfect and ſufficient.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why doth hee not ſay, <hi>This is my body of the new Teſtament,</hi> as well as, <hi>This is my bloud &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe although the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament
<pb facs="tcp:20489:11"/>
be eſtabliſhed by the offering vp of whole Chriſt:<note place="margin">Iohn 19.34</note> yet his death was more manifeſt, in the ſheding of his bloud, then in the ſufferings of his fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat commaundement did our Sauiour annex vnto theſe words?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Doe this in remembrance of me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What remembrance of Chriſt is commanded heere?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not an hiſtoricall remembrance, ſuch as is in the Diuell, nor a bare and idle remembrance, as if it did not apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto vs: but an effectuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, whereby wee doe apprehend and apply Chriſt with all his benefites to our ſelues by faith: and ſo call to minde his ſacrifice, as by it we may conceiue preſent comfort in our conſciences, and aſſured hope of euerlaſting life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat are the actions that were performed by the Diſciples, and muſt be performed by euery receiuer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To take the bread and wine at the hands of the Miniſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat doth this action ſigniffe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That in like manner wee muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb facs="tcp:20489:12"/>
Chriſt Ieſus into our hearts by a true and liuely land.<note place="margin">Iohn 1.12. and 6.35</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat doth it admoniſh vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 24.7, 8 Ephe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.17. Apoc. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> To prepare and cleanſe our hearts for the rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uing of ſo honourable a gueſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q, VVhat is the ſecond action?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> To eaſe the bread and drinke the wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat doth this action ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16 Ioh. 17.21. Ephe. 5.30</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> The vnion and communion which we haue with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is this vnion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 6.56.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a conſolating of our perſons with the perſon of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What a manner of vnion is it that we haue with Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not corporall and bodily, but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and ſupernaturall, yet reall and true.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. By what meanes is it wrought in reſpect of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.16</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By his Spirit: whereby all the faithfull are knitte vnto Chriſt, as the members of the body by ioynts &amp; ſinewes are coupled to the head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. By what meanes is it wrought in reſpect of vs;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 2.20</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By a particular application of
<pb facs="tcp:20489:12"/>
Chriſt and his merits to our owne ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth it admoniſh vs of?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Of that Chriſtian concord and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his that ought to be among the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.5 and 15.5, 6, 1 Cor. 1.10 Acts 4.32 Eſay 11.6,</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat arguments are there in the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper to perſwade vs thereunto?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. 1.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.17</note> Becauſe we all do eate of one Bread and all drinke of one Cup.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Becauſe many graines of wheate doe make one loafe of bread, and many grapes make one cup of wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. VVhat is the end of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew forth the death of Chriſt till he come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How muſt we ſhew forth the death of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Two wayes: in ſpeach, and in action.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How in ſpeach?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By giuing thankes to God for the great benefite of our redemption.<note place="margin">Pſalme 116.12 Luke 1.68</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How in action?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. 1.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.10 Galat. 6.14.</note> By ſuffering croſſes and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for Chriſt his ſake.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.4.</note> By feeling the power of Chriſts
<pb facs="tcp:20489:13"/>
death, in killing our corruptions and ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. Why doth the Apoſtle in the next place ſet downe the right vſe of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To teach vs, that the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God muſt not bee ſeparated from their holy vſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. VVhat order doth the Apoſtle obſerue in ſetting downe hereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Firſt, he ſheweth the abuſe of the Lords Supper, and then the remedy of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. VVhat is the abuſe of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To eate and drinke vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Who doe eate and drinke vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not onely ſuch as are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnworthy to come, but euen they alſo, who being worthy, doe not come as they ought.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. Who are they that are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnworthy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> There are ſome without the Church, and ſome in the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. Who are they that are without the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:13"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> All Turkes, Iews, Pagans,<note place="margin">Exodus 12.48</note> and Infidels.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. VVho are they that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. 1.</hi> All that are groſſely ignorant, though they liue neuer ſo ciuilly.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> All groſſe ſinners,<note place="margin">Matth. 7.6 and 15.26</note> though they haue neuer ſo much knowledge.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> All hypocrites.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. Who are they that may be ſaid to be worthy to come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> All the faithfull,<note place="margin">Luke 22:30</note> who for the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of Chriſt are counted worthy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. How may theſe come vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> When as not conſidering the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the Lords Supper, nor ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly examining themſelues, eyther tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ignorance or negligence, they lie in ſome ſinne without ſufficient repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. VVhat is the danger of vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receiuers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An. 1.</hi> They make themſelues guilty of a grieuous ſinne.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> They become liable to a fearefull iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. What is the ſinne whereof they are guilty?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:14"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They are guilty of the body and bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe the diſgrace done to the ſignes of Chriſt his body and bloud, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doundeth to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. VVhat is the iudgement where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto they are lyable?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They eate and drinke damnation to themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is meant by damnation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Luke 23.40 1 Pet. 4.17.</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not the ſecond death, but tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall correction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. How proue you that is taken ſo heere?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.2. and 6.11 Rom. 8.1.</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe the Apoſtle threatneth it to the Corinthians, who were iuſtified and ſanctified, and therefore not ſubiect to damnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why doth the Apoſtle ſay hee ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and drinketh iudgement to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To teach vs, that the vnworthines of any man hurteth none but himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What reaſon giueth the Apoſtle of this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe hee diſcerneth not the Lords body.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:14"/>
               <hi>Qu. What is to diſcerne the Lords body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To diſtinguiſh theſe Elements, being ſignes of Chriſts moſt precious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud from all other things, and to vſe them with that reuerence and deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is méete.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. Why is the body of Chriſt to be accounted of ſo precious and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. 1.</hi> Becauſe of the exeltation of it, being ready vnited to the Deity.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Becauſe of the merite of his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings in it, whereby he hath procured for vs eternall life.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Becauſe of the efficacie thereof in mortifying of our corruptions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Who are they that do not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Lords body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. 1.</hi> Ignorant Chriſtians, who put no difference betwéene the bread of the Sacrament and common bread: but come to the Lords table as to an ordinary feaſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> They that haue knowledge of the Myſterie, and yet doe not come with due conſideration of the dignitie thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What remedy doth the Apoſtle
<pb facs="tcp:20489:15"/>
preſcribe for preuenting of this ſinne, and for auoyding of this iudgement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That euery man trie and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. What doth that teach vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.5</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That euery man muſt haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion to iudge of his owne eſtate: or elſe he is not fit to come to the Lords Table.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. By what rule muſt we try our ſelues?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By the rule of Gods Lawe, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining our ſelues by euery commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.59.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. VVhat muſt bee the matter of our triall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Whether wee bee fitte gueſts for Gods table, or no.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. How many things are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make vs fitte?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Fine things eſpecially.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. VVhat is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. VVhat knowledge is required in this caſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A generall and a particular knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. What is the generall knowledge required?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:15"/>
               <hi>Anſ. 1.</hi> The knowledge of God, his nature, perſons, attributes and works.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> The knowledge of our natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition by originall ſinne, and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> The knowledge of the couenant of grace, concerning our redemption in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. VVhat is the particular know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The knowledge of the nature and vſe of the Sacrament, in the ſignes and actions to be performed about them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. What is the ſecond thing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> A true and ſound faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. VVhat is faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A ſure perſwaſion, that all Chriſts merites are mine, as if I had wrought them my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. Why is faith neceſſary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe in the Sacrament we receiue ſo much as wee beleeue, and no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. Doe all receiue grace preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. How then?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. 1.</hi> Such as haue ſtrong faith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede,
<pb facs="tcp:20489:16"/>
do at the inſtant receiue both grace, and a ſenſe of grace.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> A there receiue grace peraduenture, but no ſenſe and feeling of grace.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Others receiue neither grace, nor any ſenſe of grace for the preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. What is the reaſon that ſome receiue grace, but no ſenſe of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The weakeneſſe of their faith, being lke to a veſſell with a narrow mouth, that can receiue but a little water at oute.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. What is the reaſon that ſome receiue neither grace, nor any ſenſe of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe they come vnhumbled and vnprepared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Whas it to be done in both theſe caſes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Luke 17.5. Marke 9.24</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Wee muſt earneſtly pray for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the third thing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Wherein conſiſteth that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 26.75. Pſal. 119.106</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In an hearty ſorrow for our ſins paſt, and a full pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>poſe to leade a godlie life for the time to come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the fourth thing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:16"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Loue and charitie towardes our brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q VVherein conſiſteth that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In a readines to ſatiſfie for the iniuries which wee haue done to others:<note place="margin">Mat. 5.23.24</note> and to forgiue them that are done to our ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the fift and laſt thing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> A ſpeciall ſanctification.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> A renewing of our Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,<note place="margin">Geneſis 35.6 1 Sam. 16.5. Iob 1.5.</note> as we haue particularly renued our ſinnes</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu In what manner muſt this duetie of Examination be performed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An. 1.</hi> With diligence,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.40. Zeph. 2.1. 2 Cor. 13.5. Heb 4.13. Pſa, 44.20, 21</note> that we may throughly diſcerne of our eſtate.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> With ſingleneſſe of heart, becauſe wee haue to deale with God that can not be deceiued.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Speedily without delay.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Conſtantly, without giuing ouer, till wee haue found that we ſeeke for.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> With earneſt prayer to God, for the direction and aſſiſtance of his Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. VVhy doth the Apoſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund euerie man to examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:17"/>
euery man to examine himſelfe?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.11</note>
               <hi>An. 1.</hi> Becauſe euery man knoweth himſelfe beſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2,</hi> Becauſe a godly man will be moſt faithfull to himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.12 Galat. 6.5</note>
               <hi>3.</hi> Becauſe euery man muſt chiefly giue account to God for himſelfe, and not for others, further then he is charged with them by vertue of his calling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. How doth the Apoſtle prooue, that the vnworthy receuing of the Lords Supper cauſeth temporall iudgements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By the preſent experience which the <hi>Corinthians</hi> had in themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What was that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> For this cauſe many are weake and ſicke among you, and many ſléep, that is, are dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. What doe you generally learne from thence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That as all ſinne, ſo eſpecially vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy receiuing is the cauſe of outward calamities.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. Why doth the Apoſtle make mention of diuers kindes of iudgements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28. tot. and 32.34 Leuit. 26. tot.</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To teach vs, that the Lord hath varietie of iudgements to inflict vpon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:17"/>
               <hi>Que. VVhy are the iudgements ſet downe, one greater then another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To teach vs,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.14 Amos 4.6, 7, 12</note> that there are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées of Gods iudgements: if we can not profit by the leſſer, hee can and will inflict greater.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. Doth God ſtrike his children with temporall death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes ſometimes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the reaſon thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1</hi> For the chaſtiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſins paſt.<note place="margin">Lu. 23.39, 40 1 Ki. 13.24, 26</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> For preuenting ſinne to come.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ki. 14.12, 13</note> That they may not ſée the euil and miſery that is to come.<note place="margin">2 Kin. 22.20 Eſay 57.1</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. VVhy is death compared to a ſleepe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 57.2 Apoc. 14.13</note> Becauſe in it the godly reſt from their labours.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Becauſe it is as eaſie,<note place="margin">Iohn 11.11.</note> for Chriſt to raiſe the dead out of their graues, as it is for vs to awake our friends out of ſléepe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. VVhat remedy hath the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle preſcribed for preuenting of theſe iudgements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That we iudge our ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. What is meant by iudging our ſelues?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:18"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To take that courſe againſt our ſelues, which is taken with a malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As Ioſhua 7 16, 17, 18.</note>
               <hi>Anſw. 1.</hi> To make diligent ſearch to finde out our ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> To arraigne our ſelues before the barre of Gods iudgement.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> To frame a bill of Inditement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſelues.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.4.</note>
               <hi>4.</hi> To giue euidence againſt our ſelues.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> To giue vp a verdict againſt our ſelues, and to pleade guilty.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.4. Dan. 9.7 1 Kin. 20.32</note>
               <hi>6.</hi> To pronounce ſentence of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt our ſelues.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> To play the executioners, and to put our ſinnes to death, <hi>Coloſſ. 3.5. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. 5.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. But will not God take vs at the aduantage, and condemne vs out of our owne mouthes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn 1.9 Prov. 28.13</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, if we iudge our ſelues, wee ſhall not be iudged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. But wee ſee the godly notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſubiect to many outward miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> True: but their croſſes are no
<pb facs="tcp:20489:18"/>
puniſhments of their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. What then is the end of Gods correcting his children?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> There is a two-fold end, one in this life, and another in the life to come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. What is the end of Gods cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in this life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As a louing father to nurture his children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. Wherefore doth God nurture his children?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. 1.</hi> To make them learne.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.71.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que. What leſſons may a man learne vnder the Croſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. 1.</hi> To ſée his ſinnes.<note place="margin">Gen. 42.21. Pſa. 30.6, 7, 8</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> To ſée his owne frailety, and to fly to God for ſuccour.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> To ſee the vanity of all earthly things, and to ſeeke for an inheritance in heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Wherefore elſe doth God nurture his children?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> To breake them of their wills.<note place="margin">Ierem. 31.18. Pſal. 119.67.120</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> To kéepe them in awe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the end of Gods corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for the life to come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> That wee may not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with the wicked world.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20489:19"/>
               <hi>Queſt. What may wee learne from hence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.11.</note>
               <hi>Anſ. 1.</hi> Not to meaſure affliction by the preſent ſenſe, but by the fruit that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth after it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 41.1. Eccleſ. 9.1.</note>
               <hi>2.</hi> To iudge wiſely of the afflicted, and not to determine of any man by his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eſtate in this life.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20489:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
